in this video we are going to go over
the task of segmenting the structure
using ITK snap segmentation tool and
converting the result into dicom
representation using dcmqi converters
in preparation to this
video recording I saved the dicom
dataset into a temporary directory and
installed ITK snap on my computer
i'm going to launch ITK snap and
load the image data which is a dicom
series and you will find a link to the
dicom series that I use here in the
supporting materials for this video so
as I can see it's an MRI series of
the brain and for this simple example
I'm going to segment ventricles just to
make it quick for the demonstration
purposes I'm not going to describe your
how segmentation is done using
ITK snap in detail but you can check
out the ITK snap homepage for the very
excellent tutorials that they provide
that should be able to help you with a
segmentation itself our tutorial is
focusing on the conversion task and I'm
going to just go over the steps to
create the final result so I created the
speed image I'm going to create this
label which i will call ventricles know
the color of this label next once
the speed image is ready I'm
going to I create initialization for the
segmentation process I'm going to place
some bubbles and I am going to launch
the segmentation as you see the
segmentation contour is evolving and very
quickly it covers the space inside the
ventricles looks good to me so I'm going
to stop you can see the result is overlay
here and as a three-dimensional
structure here so that's that's the data
said that I want to export into dicom
and in ITK snap i will use the
segmentation export into nrrd image
format it's a very popular format in the
image
processing field in clinical image
analysis and I'm going to save this
result as nrrd file into my temporary
directory side-by-side with my dicom
data
In our directory we have the folder with the
source dicom data and we have the
ventricles segmentation result saved as
nrrd file what we have to do next is to
create the metadata saved in json to
facilitate the task of conversion to
help with this task we created a web
application that allows you to populate
in a visual convenient manner different
attributes that are required by the
converter so for the content creator
name i'm going to put my name for the
series description which is a free text
field segmentation of ventricles for the
body part examined it's a brain here i'm
going to choose the list that defines
the terminology to be used and I will
need to populate this form for each of
the segments in our instance we have
only one segment I will put again
description of this segment it's
ventricles are segments algorithm name ITK
snap for the segmented category the
choice here is anatomical structure and
now here I can start typing and I
see that brain ventricle is good match i
will initialize the color to be the same
color that we used in ITK snap that also
can be communicated in the metadata file
and now one very important attribute
here is this label ID label ID is the
number that links the section of the
JSON file described in this segment with
the label saved in the nrrd file so if
i go back to ITK snap i can see that
the label that i was assigned in the
output segmentation image is five
this means i need to specify five are in
my metadata now i'm ready i generated
this JSON content i will download and
save it into this
same directory where my segmentation and
source dicom data is located so now we
should be all set to do the conversion I
pre-populated this command line but
let's take a moment to look what is here
the important argument to the
run command is this dash v command that
essentially points the
converter to the content of the
directory with the beta so that
directory where I have all my data will
be mapped to /tmp/dcmqi directory and
now I need to use the command line
arguments to specify the input dicom
directory that's where the source they
dicom files are located the path to the
input metadata in JSON format input
image list which is short just one file
with the ventricles segmentation and the
filename to store the result of
conversion in dicom I run the converter
and it's completed successfully and now
i can see the result of conversion they
can file saved in the same directory